Guide to the Frank Mace McFarland Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Frank Mace McFarland papers
1893-1943
SC0014
McFarland, Frank Mace, 1869-1951.
0.5 Linear feet
Correspondence and writing of Dr. MacFarland; includes correspondence with colleagues; letters from his student Donald B. Tresidder, 1918 and 1940-43; and correspondence with fellow members of the Stanford Class of 1893 and records pertaining to their 25th reunion, 1918. Correspondents include Charles H. O'Donoghue, L. Ward Bannister, A. H. Barnhisel, Carl S. Carlsmith, W. B. Clark, Helen Cubberley, Charles N. Ellinwood, and William A. Hilton. Other items include sketch books of Mrs. MacFarland; and a notebook including notes on the two voyages of the yacht, "The Naturalist" (1889) and MacFarland's log of bicycle trips around Stanford, San Jose, the Peninsula, and the California coast.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of the estate of Mrs. Frank MacFarland, 1964.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of histology at Stanford (1892-1934; emeritus, 1934-1951) and one of the organizers of the Hopkins Marine Biological Station at Pacific Grove. MacFarland was in charge of Hopkins Marine Station from 1910-1913 and co-director 1915-1917.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence and writing of Dr. MacFarland; includes correspondence with colleagues; letters from his student Donald B. Tresidder, 1918 and 1940-43; and correspondence with fellow members of the Stanford Class of 1893 and records pertaining to their 25th reunion, 1918. Correspondents include Charles H. O'Donoghue, L. Ward Bannister, A. H. Barnhisel, Carl S. Carlsmith, W. B. Clark, Helen Cubberley, Charles N. Ellinwood, and William A. Hilton. Other items include sketch books of Mrs. MacFarland; and a notebook including notes on the two voyages of the yacht, "The Naturalist" (1889) and MacFarland's log of bicycle trips around Stanford, San Jose, the Peninsula, and the California coast.
Access Terms
Bannister, L. Ward.; Barnhisel, Arthur H.; Carlsmith, Carl S.; Clark, W. B.; Cubberley, Helen Van Uxem, d. 1952.; Ellinwood, Charles N.; Hilton, William Atwood, 1878-; Hopkins Marine Station--Faculty.; MacFarland, Frank Mace, 1869-1951.; MacFarland, Frank, Mrs.; McFarland, Frank Mace, 1869-1951.; O'Donoghue, Charles Henry, 1885-; Stanford University. Class of 1893.; Stanford University. Department of Histology. Faculty.; Tresidder, Donald Bertrand, 1894-1948
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Biographical materials (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1893: list of officers and correspondence concerning reunion and laying of class plate, 1917-18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: B, 1912-23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes: Frank C. Baker, L. Ward Bannister, A. H. Barnhisel, Bane (?) Brockett, Richard Buchanan, and Mrs. L. M. Burwell
  - Correspondence: C, 1902-38 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes: Murray A. Campbell, Carl S. Carlsmith, W. B. Clark, D. A. Cockerell, W. W. Collins, Charles E. Cox, Ellwood Cubberley, and Helen Cubberley
  - Correspondence: D-H, 1905-28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes: Chas. H. O'Donoghue, Chas. N. Ellinwood, Barton W. Everman, H. G. C. Hallock, Samuel Henshaw, W. A. Hilton, Lou Henry Hoover
  - Correspondence: L-S, 1912-55 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes: G. A. Lawrence, D. H. Lebrun, John A. Nowell, Walter Ranson, E. L. Rich, A. R. Sawyer, Waldo S. Schmitt (letter from Mrs. MacFarland), Walter O. Smith, and J. W. Spengel
  - Correspondence: T-W, 1912-40 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes: Donald Tresidder, J. Versleys, Arthur Washburn, C. B. Whittier, John McKinlay Wight, Ray Lyman Wilbur, and Henry D. Wild
  - Notebook: voyage of "Naturalist" 1889 and "Cyclometer" record, 1896-97 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publication: Cellulare Studien an Mollusken-Eiern, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publications: Preliminary Account of the Dorididae of Monterey Bay, California; Opisthobranchiate Mollusca from Monterey Bay, California, and Vicinity; The Nudibranch Family Dironidae; In Memoriam Nettie Maria Stevens, 1905-1913 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Opisthobranchiate Mollusca of the Branner-Agassiz Expedition to Brazil, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Publication: The Morphology of the Nudibranch Genus Hancockia; Opisthobranchiate Mollusca; The Acanthodoridiae of the California Coast; Drepania, a Genus of Nudibranchiate Mollusks New to California; A New Species of Corambe from the Pacific Coast of North America; Edwin Chapin Starks, 1923-1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook of O. H. MacFarland, 1905-1908 (Box 1, Folder 13)